<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences on Alex K Gold Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/conferences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences on Alex K Gold Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/conferences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #2: Failure’s Coming, Get Ready!</title>
      <link>/2019/01/23/upgrading-to-r-2-failure-s-coming-get-ready/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/23/upgrading-to-r-2-failure-s-coming-get-ready/</guid>
      <description>This is definitely the most personal, and the most painful of my upgrading to R lessons. But first, here’s a basic outline of something that many first-time managers go through. I can guarantee something like this will happen if you’re managing a team upgrading to R.
options(gganimate.nframes = 400, gganimate.fps = 6, gganimate.end_pause = 10) morale &amp;lt;- c(2, 3, 4.5, 3, 3, 2.6, 2.0, 0.5, 1.3, 2, 3.5, 4.0) prod &amp;lt;- c(1, 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #1: Excitement &gt;&gt; Skills</title>
      <link>/2019/01/20/upgrading-to-r-1-excitement-skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/20/upgrading-to-r-1-excitement-skills/</guid>
      <description>This is the first in a series of posts sharing some insights on upgrading to R. See the index post for others.
Whether you’re a team leader trying to take your group to the next level, or an indvidual contributor just trying to infect your org with R love, finding companions is really important. Finding the right people will determine whether you end up part of a crack R team or fall back to whatever you’re doing now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R at RStudio::conf(2019)</title>
      <link>/2019/01/19/upgrading-to-r-at-rstudio-conf-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/19/upgrading-to-r-at-rstudio-conf-2019/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago, I was beyond thrilled to be chosen to give an e-poster at RStudio::conf(2019) on the topic of Upgrading to R. I had such a blast talking to people who are trying to get their team to use more R, sharing some of the lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over the last few years. My slides are available online, but I&amp;rsquo;d also like to share some of the things I spoke with people about, and a little on how I made the slides.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>