<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences on Alex K Gold Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/conferences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences on Alex K Gold Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/conferences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #3: Be the Data Engineer they Need</title>
      <link>/2019/02/20/upgrading-to-r-3-be-the-data-engineer-they-need/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/20/upgrading-to-r-3-be-the-data-engineer-they-need/</guid>
      <description>When I first went to data conferences, I assumed that EVERYONE else was pulling data from a supercomputer-backed Spark cluster, immaculately maintained by an army of data engineers. Needless to say, that was not my data infrastructure.
 To be more succinct, most of the “data infrastructure” I’ve worked with has just been csv files. And our ETL processes – cleaning csv files to output more csv files (or rds).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #2: Failure’s Coming, Get Ready!</title>
      <link>/2019/02/08/upgrading-to-r-2-failure-s-coming-get-ready/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/08/upgrading-to-r-2-failure-s-coming-get-ready/</guid>
      <description>As a new manager working with my team of data scientists, upgrading to R meant doing something new, and something hard. As I should’ve known, new + hard is a great recipe for mistakes and failures. I learned a lot from those mistakes - lessons that I couldn’t have anticipated ahead of time. I’ll share my surprising (and less surprising) things I learned from one particular big failure in this blog post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #1: Excitement &gt;&gt; Skills</title>
      <link>/2019/01/20/upgrading-to-r-1-excitement-skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/20/upgrading-to-r-1-excitement-skills/</guid>
      <description>This is the first in a series of posts sharing some insights on upgrading to R. See the index post for others.
Whether you’re a team leader trying to take your group to the next level, or an indvidual contributor just trying to use more R (or get your organization to do so), it’s really important to find other people to join you on the journey. If you manage to find the right people, they’ll become a crack R team (relatively) quickly or will help you upgrade your own skills.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R at RStudio::conf(2019)</title>
      <link>/2019/01/19/upgrading-to-r-at-rstudio-conf-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/19/upgrading-to-r-at-rstudio-conf-2019/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago, I was beyond thrilled to be chosen to give an e-poster at RStudio::conf(2019) on the topic of Upgrading to R. I had such a blast talking to people who are trying to get their team to use more R, sharing some of the lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over the last few years. My slides are available online, but I&amp;rsquo;d also like to share some of the things I spoke with people about, and a little on how I made the slides.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>