<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Alex K Gold Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Alex K Gold Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #3: Be the Data Engineer you Need</title>
      <link>/2019/02/20/upgrading-to-r-3-be-the-data-engineer-they-need/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/20/upgrading-to-r-3-be-the-data-engineer-they-need/</guid>
      <description>When I first went to data conferences, I assumed that EVERYONE else was pulling data from a supercomputer-backed Spark cluster, immaculately maintained by an army of data engineers. Needless to say, that was not my data infrastructure.
 To be more succinct, most of the “data infrastructure” I’ve worked with has just been csv files. And our ETL processes – cleaning csv files to output more csv files (or rds).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #2: Failure’s Coming, Get Ready!</title>
      <link>/2019/02/08/upgrading-to-r-2-failure-s-coming-get-ready/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/08/upgrading-to-r-2-failure-s-coming-get-ready/</guid>
      <description>As a new manager working with my team of data scientists, upgrading to R meant doing something new, and something hard. As I should’ve known, new + hard is a great recipe for mistakes and failures. I learned a lot from those mistakes - lessons that I couldn’t have anticipated ahead of time. I’ll share my surprising (and less surprising) things I learned from one particular big failure in this blog post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R #1: Excitement &gt;&gt; Skills</title>
      <link>/2019/01/20/upgrading-to-r-1-excitement-skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/20/upgrading-to-r-1-excitement-skills/</guid>
      <description>This is the first in a series of posts sharing some insights on upgrading to R. See the index post for others.
Whether you’re a team leader trying to take your group to the next level, or an indvidual contributor just trying to infect your org with R love, finding companions is really important. Finding the right people will determine whether you end up part of a crack R team or fall back to whatever you’re doing now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to R at RStudio::conf(2019)</title>
      <link>/2019/01/19/upgrading-to-r-at-rstudio-conf-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/19/upgrading-to-r-at-rstudio-conf-2019/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago, I was beyond thrilled to be chosen to give an e-poster at RStudio::conf(2019) on the topic of Upgrading to R. I had such a blast talking to people who are trying to get their team to use more R, sharing some of the lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over the last few years. My slides are available online, but I&amp;rsquo;d also like to share some of the things I spoke with people about, and a little on how I made the slides.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Best Computer For Data Scientists</title>
      <link>/2018/03/23/the-best-computer-for-data-scientists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/23/the-best-computer-for-data-scientists/</guid>
      <description>Is whatever you like! I am generally quite predisposed to using Macs for programming activities. The native shell support, easy access to SSH, git, and a built-in hotkey combination for screenshots (cmd+ctrl+shift+4 for a movable window you can position and paste from) are all killer features. That on top of the fact that Mac laptops are the only ones with touchpads good enough that I don&amp;rsquo;t crave a mouse, means that I&amp;rsquo;ve fully gone over to the cult of Mac.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Shareable R Workflow</title>
      <link>/2017/12/20/a-shareable-r-workflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/20/a-shareable-r-workflow/</guid>
      <description>If you, like me, work primarily in R, I bet you&amp;rsquo;ve pulled a colleague&amp;rsquo;s scripts, tried to load the data and, File Not Found Error.
Argh!!
Thanks to Jenny Bryan&amp;rsquo;s awesome blog post, I learned there&amp;rsquo;s a better solution that&amp;rsquo;s already made me overhaul my sharing workflow.
Thanks to the combination of RStudio Projects in RStudio and the here package, my woes with manually setting directories are over.
For a while, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using RStudio Projects since they&amp;rsquo;re a great way to keep work on different projects distinct.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rvest is awesome for web scraping!</title>
      <link>/2017/07/02/rvest-is-awesome-for-web-scraping/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/07/02/rvest-is-awesome-for-web-scraping/</guid>
      <description>The rvest package is awesome. No surprise there, it&amp;rsquo;s a Hadley Wickham jont. I&amp;rsquo;m in the early stages of a small project looking at goodreads quotes. I think I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to predict popular quotes. Then maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll build a neural network to generate quotes trained on these. Stay tuned.
Anyway, I wanted to extract the top quotes on goodreads, and rvest made it super easy! I&amp;rsquo;d suggest this tutorial for anyone just getting started.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build My Own Neural Network</title>
      <link>/2017/06/29/build-my-own-neural-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/06/29/build-my-own-neural-network/</guid>
      <description>If you, like me have a pretty solid background in statistics and matrix algebra but don&amp;rsquo;t know much about deep learning or neural networks, I highly recommend the ebook Neural Networks and Deep Learning by Michael Nielsen.
The Ebook The book is mostly focused on the math and mechanics of deep learning, as opposed to building and using neural networks in a production context. It&amp;rsquo;s a really excellent introduction to what a neural network is and how they learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Stats NYC 2017</title>
      <link>/2017/04/23/r-stats-nyc-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/23/r-stats-nyc-2017/</guid>
      <description>Friday and Saturday of this weekend was the 2017 RStatsNYC conference. With the small exception of remarkably uncomfortable chairs, the conference was fantastic (and great food!). There was a remarkable variety in what the speakers covered &amp;ndash; from deep thoughts on the ethics and philosophy of doing data science, to some super useful RStudio tips and tricks and everything in between. I decided to take my notes from the two days and post below in case there&amp;rsquo;s things anyone else might find useful.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>